Rakibul Islam

Email: raakibul.uap@gmail.com | Webpage: raaakibul.github.io | Phone: +880-1315396692 Dhaka, Bangladesh

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am deeply inspired by the potential of Machine Learning and Deep Learning to shape the future of technology and society. My research passion lies in building the intelligent systems. All that not only pushes the boundaries of innovation but also addresses real-world challenges in meaningful ways. I strive to develop scalable, practical, and human-centered machine learning solutions that can be widely implemented to improve lives and advance the frontiers of artificial intelligence.

Research Areas: Machine Learning, Applied Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Computer Vision, Artificial Intelligence

EDUCATION

University of Asia Pacific

Dhaka, Bangladesh | Sept. 2018 - June 2023

Bachelor of Computer Science and Engineering

Major Courses: Structured Programming, Data Structure and Algorithms, Object Oriented Programming, Database, Software Engineering, Computer Networks, Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Probability & Statistics, Data Communications, Linear Algebra, Multivariable Calculus, etc.

Thesis Topic: Deep Learning-Based Background Noise Classification and Reduction for Audio Enhancement

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Bdian Research Trainee

Dhaka, Bangladesh | Sept. 2022 - Dec. 2022

Researcher at Youth society For Research and Action.

Understanding research methodology in real-world scenarios, including proposing topics, designing studies, and selecting methodologies.

WORK EXPERIENCE

CareTutors

Dhaka, Bangladesh | Oct. 2023 – Present

Instructor at Largest online and offline based tutoring platform.

I taught physics, chemistry, mathematics, and programming languages (Python, C, C++, JavaScript for Web development) to high school and college students through in-person and group-based lessons.

Industrial Trainee

Dhaka, Bangladesh | Dec. 2022 - May 2023

Software Engr. Intern at BrogrammersLab

I learned to approach problem-solving calmly and focus on solutions. Effective communication and collaboration are essential in a team and time management is the most valuable lesson I gained.

SKILLS

Programming Languages: Python, JavaScript, SQL, C/C++, Java

Python Packages: Pytorch, OpenCV, Pandas, Matplotlib, Keras, Sci-kit learn, TensorFlow **Web Technologies:** HTML, CSS, SASC, Bootstrap, JavaScript, TypeScript, React, Json

Tools: Microsoft Word, Microsoft Excel, Latex, Visual Studio, Microsoft SQL Server, MySQL, Power BI, Git

Project Management: Communication Skills (Written & Verbal), Quantitative Skills, Initiative, Interpersonal

Skills, Teamwork, Time Management, etc. **Languages:** English (Native), Bengali (Fluent)

THESIS PUBLICATIONS

Deep Learning-Based Background Noise Classification and Reduction for Audio Enhancement. – under review

PROFESSIONAL TRAINING & CERTIFICATES

2024 - Mathematics for Machine Learning and Data Science (3 Courses) by Luis Serrano | DeepLearning.AI

- · Linear Algebra for Machine Learning and Data Science
- Calculus for Machine Learning and Data Science
- Probability & Statistics for Machine Learning & Data Science

2024 - Machine Learning Specialization (3 Courses) by Andrew NG | DeepLearning.AI & Stanford University

- Supervised Machine Learning: Regression and Classification
- Advanced Learning Algorithms
- Unsupervised Learning, Recommenders, Reinforcement Learning

2024 - Learn SQL Basics for Data Science Specialization (1 Course) | University of California, Davis

SQL for Data Science by Sadie St. Lawrence

2024 - IBM Data Analyst Professional Certificate (1 Course) | IBM

Data Visualization with Python by Saishruthi Swaminathan and Dr. Pooja

2024 - Data Science Foundations Specialization (1 Course) | IBM

What is Data Science by Alex Aklson

2024 - Google Data Analytics Professional Certificate (1 Course) | Google

Foundations: Data, Data, Everywhere

2022 - Bdian Research Trainee certificate

REFERENCES

Tanjina Helaly (Advisor)
Assistant Professor, University of Asia Pacific
Department of Computer Science & Engr.

Rashik Rahman (Thesis Supervisor)
Lecturer, University of Asia Pacific
Department of Computer Science & Engr.

Dr. Aloke Kumar Saha Professor, University of Asia Pacific Department of Computer Science and Engineering